<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>Silander Lab</title>
 <link href="/" rel="self"/>
 <link href=""/>
 <updated>2018-10-10T14:46:27+13:00</updated>
 <id></id>
 <author>
   <name>Dr. Olin Silander</name>
   <email>olinsilander@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Dr. Olin Silander</title>
   <link href="/team/olin-silander"/>
   <updated>2018-10-07T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>/team/olin-silander</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am a Senior Lecturer in Genetics at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.massey.ac.nz/massey/explore/departments/institute-natural-mathematical-sciences/institute-natural-mathematical-sciences_home.cfm&quot;&gt;Institute of Natural and Mathematical Sciences&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My research focuses on microbial evolution. Current projects include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How gene expression noice evolves&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How &lt;em&gt;E.coli&lt;/em&gt; responds to and learns from environmental signals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How behavioural responses in &lt;em&gt;E.coli&lt;/em&gt; evolve&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;research-interests&quot;&gt;Research Interests&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evolution&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;E.coli&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transcription&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Genomics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Markéta Vlkova</title>
   <link href="/team/marketa-vlkova"/>
   <updated>2018-10-07T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>/team/marketa-vlkova</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Kelly Hong</title>
   <link href="/team/kelly-hong"/>
   <updated>2018-10-07T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>/team/kelly-hong</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Georgia Breckell</title>
   <link href="/team/georgia-breckell"/>
   <updated>2018-10-07T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>/team/georgia-breckell</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Daying Wen</title>
   <link href="/team/daying-wen"/>
   <updated>2018-10-07T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>/team/daying-wen</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>New Website designed</title>
   <link href="/news/new-website-design"/>
   <updated>2018-10-07T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>/news/new-website-design</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;New website designed and this is the first news post.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Silander Lab</title>
   <link href="/misc/home/home"/>
   <updated>2018-10-07T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>/misc/home/home</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are interested in the interplay between phenotypic plasticity and phenotypic noise, and how these two traits have evolved in natural isolates of &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt;. To gain insight into this problem, we employ methods that allow us to observe single cells and their response to changes in environmental signals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To measure changes in cellular physiology and transcription, we use quantitative image analysis. Some of this is done through a collaboration with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cadmo.ethz.ch/as/people/members/fjug/personal_home&quot;&gt;Florian Jug&lt;/a&gt;, who is now at MPI Dresden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are interested in the evolution of novel transcriptional control (e.g. changes in start sites, mRNA levels, or new small RNAs). We use RNA-seq of natural isolates of &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; to quantify these changes. We also use these data in conjunction with information on protein levels to understand how selection differentially acts on mRNA and protein levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We use experimental evolution to in conjunction with information from natural isolates of &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; to gain evolutionary insights in all of our research.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>About</title>
   <link href="/misc/about"/>
   <updated>2018-10-07T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>/misc/about</id>
   <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;purpose&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;purpose&quot;&gt;Purpose&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where you’ll find the most up-to-date information on who we are, what we’re working on, what we’ve done, and how we did it. And how you can, too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;contact&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;contact&quot;&gt;Contact&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mailing-address&quot;&gt;Mailing Address&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Olin Silander&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Institute of Natural and Mathematical Sciences&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Massey University&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Private Bag 102 904&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auckland, New Zealand&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.co.nz/maps/place/Eastbourne+Rd,+Albany,+Auckland+0632/@-36.7341619,174.6921899,18z/data=!4m5!3m4!1s0x6d0d3bf4286e83ef:0x2b28e609744ba117!8m2!3d-36.7341254!4d174.6929892&quot;&gt;Physical Location&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phone&quot;&gt;Phone&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lab:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Office:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fax:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;design&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;design-and-implementation&quot;&gt;Design and Implementation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This website was inspired by Dr. &lt;a href=&quot;http://bedford.io/team/trevor-bedford/&quot;&gt;Trevor Bedford&lt;/a&gt;’s lab website and adapted from &lt;a href=&quot;http://drummondlab.org/about.html#purpose&quot;&gt;Drummond Lab&lt;/a&gt;’s website which was based on Bedford Lab website. More technical details are below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The site uses &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllbootstrap.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt;, and is deployed using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netlify.com/&quot;&gt;Netlify&lt;/a&gt;, which makes hosting a breeze. Keeping with a major Jekyll Bootstrap idea, the site separates content and presentation. Presentation information is stored in a new theme, the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;lab&lt;/code&gt; theme, which may be useful to other research groups setting up sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By using &lt;a href=&quot;http://sass-lang.com/&quot;&gt;Sass&lt;/a&gt; for stylesheets, the site gets virtually all the advantages of using &lt;a href=&quot;http://lesscss.org/&quot;&gt;Less&lt;/a&gt;, while exploiting native Sass support in [GitHub Pages]. The site uses &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/fonts&quot;&gt;Google Fonts&lt;/a&gt; as well, primarily &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/fonts/specimen/Open+Sans&quot;&gt;Open Sans&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The site’s source code is freely available on &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. All code is placed under the MIT license. You’re welcome to borrow / repurpose code to build your own site, and if you do, I’d appreciate attribution and a link back [here].&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Monitoring single-cell gene regulation under dynamically controllable conditions with integrated microfluidics and software</title>
   <link href="/papers/paper/ecoli-microfluidics"/>
   <updated>2018-01-15T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>/papers/paper/ecoli-microfluidics</id>
   <content type="html">
&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much is still not understood about how gene regulatory interactions control cell fate decisions in single cells, in part due to the difficulty of directly observing gene regulatory processes in vivo. We introduce here a novel integrated setup consisting of a microfluidic chip and accompanying analysis software that enable long-term quantitative tracking of growth and gene expression in single cells. The dual-input Mother Machine (DIMM) chip enables controlled and continuous variation of external conditions, allowing direct observation of gene regulatory responses to changing conditions in single cells. The Mother Machine Analyzer (MoMA) software achieves unprecedented accuracy in segmenting and tracking cells, and streamlines high-throughput curation with a novel leveraged editing procedure. We demonstrate the power of the method by uncovering several novel features of an iconic gene regulatory program: the induction of Escherichia coli’s lac operon in response to a switch from glucose to lactose.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Sticking together to survive stress</title>
   <link href="/blog/about-adaptive-phase-separation"/>
   <updated>2017-03-09T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>/blog/about-adaptive-phase-separation</id>
   <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;We’ve just published a &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/paper/adaptive-phase-separation&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; on how a protein’s ability to form hydrogels allows cells to sense and respond to stress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-bit-of-background&quot;&gt;A bit of background&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like us, cells react to stresses like heat, starvation, and poison. All these stresses cause clumps of molecules to form inside cells. This clumping—aggregation—looks like damaged proteins sticking together. But in our last &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/paper/endogenous-aggregates&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;, we showed that instead, these clumps look like they’re a cellular response, not just signs of damage. (See our &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/about-endogenous-aggregates&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; on it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re going to go back to the Cellular Institute with its manicured grounds and main building. Happy workers (proteins) go about their often inscrutable business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/cellular-institute-unstressed.png&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Institute is constantly dealing with awful changes in its environment. The mission is to survive, even to keep growing, during those tough times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/environmental-and-growth-reports.png&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The picture that came out of our &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/about-endogenous-aggregates&quot;&gt;earlier study&lt;/a&gt; suggested that, overall, the clumping in cells was an organized, reversible process, consistent with a coordinated effort to survive tough times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about for specific proteins? How can you tell if clumping is stress-inflicted damage or an adaptive response? A key test is to see what happens when you stop the clumping during stress. Stopping damage during stress should make cells healthier. Stopping an adaptive stress response, on the other hand, would make cells sicker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;doesnt-sound-too-complicated&quot;&gt;Doesn’t sound too complicated&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Easy for you to say, headline! In our study, we had to first find a protein that formed clumps during stress, then figure out how to control its clumping without screwing up a bunch of other stuff (which involved quite a bit of figuring out why it formed clumps, physically, and which bits of the molecule were responsible).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing all that required working on the protein in isolation in a test tube, so then we had to put the protein back into cells  to see if it worked the same way. Finally, we could expose those cells to stress and see how they responded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-did-we-do&quot;&gt;What did we do?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We picked out a specific protein that formed clumps during stress: poly(A)-binding protein, which is nicknamed Pab1 in baker’s yeast, our beautiful and hardy model organism. (Relatives of Pab1 are found in essentially every cell that has a nucleus, from plants to parasites to people.) We purified Pab1, put it in a dish, and exposed it to the same intracellular conditions that follow stress and are thought to cause clumping, heat and pH.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeast cells like to live in acidic (low-pH) environments, but keep their insides at neutral pH. When cells get stressed, their internal pH drops, becoming more acidic. That, others have argued, might cause clumping during non-heat stresses like starvation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/heat-starvation-ph-at-cell-institute.png&quot; width=&quot;75%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-did-we-find&quot;&gt;What did we find?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we discovered that Pab1 “clumping” was something rather specific and wonderful: &lt;strong&gt;phase separation&lt;/strong&gt; into hydrogel droplets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phase separation is like a flash mob. Under certain conditions, suddenly, from a mixture of two types of molecules, one type surges together, separating from the other (“demixing”) like oil droplets from water. Bunches of recent studies have shown proteins doing this trick, usually under exotic conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/phase-separation-cartoon.png&quot; width=&quot;75%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pab1 phase-separates in response to both pH and temperature, right at the stress-associated ranges of each one. It’s one of the coolest results in the paper: Pab1 is an extraordinarily sensitive &lt;em&gt;sensor of stress&lt;/em&gt;, particularly temperature. You might be surprised to know that how yeast cells sense temperature has been a bit of mystery…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;back-into-the-cell&quot;&gt;Back into the cell&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We figured out a way to make Pab1 phase separate at lower or higher temperatures. Remember our key test? That let us make cells with proteins that couldn’t get together during stress. And guess what we found?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/disrupting-phase-separation.png&quot; width=&quot;75%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cells with Pab1 molecules that didn’t stick together during stress couldn’t grow during stress. This happened during heat shock, and during starvation, too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ultimately-its-about-fitness&quot;&gt;Ultimately, it’s about fitness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s been a bunch of beautiful work on phase separation, hydrogel formation, and other quinary phenomena. (&lt;strong&gt;Quinary&lt;/strong&gt;, a term introduced by Stuart Edelstein, refers to a step beyond traditional quaternary structures to structures involving undefined numbers of molecules.) But showing that these phenomena are actually good for cells, as opposed to just gorgeous curiosities, has been challenging. Pab1 delivered for us!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/quinary-academy-certificate.png&quot; width=&quot;75%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dive-in&quot;&gt;Dive in!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/paper/adaptive-phase-separation&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; was five years from initial discovery to publication. There’s a lot in there (though the reviewers wanted oh so much more!). For experts, our results are full of surprises. First author &lt;a href=&quot;/team/josh-riback&quot;&gt;Josh&lt;/a&gt; has blogged about some of the &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/polymer-biophysics-in-action&quot;&gt;biophysical aspects&lt;/a&gt; and co-first author &lt;a href=&quot;/team/chris-katanski&quot;&gt;Chris&lt;/a&gt; has blogged about the &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/Pab1-Demixing-FAQ&quot;&gt;in vivo aspects&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there’s much more to do. How, exactly, does Pab1’s phase separation help the cell? We share some ideas in the paper. How, exactly, does Pab1 sense temperature and pH? Watch this space as the story continues to, well, come together.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Behind the scenes of Pab1 demixing</title>
   <link href="/blog/Pab1-Demixing-FAQ"/>
   <updated>2017-03-09T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>/blog/Pab1-Demixing-FAQ</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi, I’m Chris. I’m a student in the Drummond lab and coauthor on the &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/paper/adaptive-phase-separation&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; “&lt;em&gt;Stress-Triggered Phase Separation Is an Adaptive, Evolutionarily Tuned Response&lt;/em&gt;.” When presenting this work, I’ve been asked a few questions repeatedly that I will answer in a &lt;strong&gt;FAQ&lt;/strong&gt; section. I’ll also share an anecdote about the challenges of delineating Pab1’s role in the stress response from its many other functions. I hope the story emphasizes the importance of &lt;strong&gt;endogenous protein expression levels&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;faqs&quot;&gt;FAQs:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-δp-yeast-strain-grows-better-at-high-temperature-than-the-other-demixing-impaired-mutants--what-gives&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The ΔP yeast strain grows better at high temperature than the other demixing-impaired mutants – what gives?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How can a few point mutations in the P-domain have a greater fitness effect than deleting the domain wholesale? In &lt;strong&gt;figure 6F&lt;/strong&gt;, when we compare the growth at 40° C of yeast expressing Pab1 variants; mutants “MV-&amp;gt;A” and “MVFY-&amp;gt;AGPNQ” show a major growth defect. These mutants show a greater defect than the strain expressing Pab1ΔP. This is result is most easily rationalized through the lens of demixing: Pab1ΔP demixes more robustly than either of the mutants; therefore it grows more robustly at high temperature. &lt;strong&gt;Figure 6G&lt;/strong&gt; illustrates the relation between growth and Pab1 demixing. The related question, “how can a few point mutations have a greater effect on demixing than deleting the domain wholesale?” remains open. Josh discusses this point in greater detail in &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/polymer-biophysics-in-action&quot;&gt;his blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-do-mutations-to-the-p-domain-affect-stress-granule-formation&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;How do mutations to the P-domain affect stress granule formation?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t know. The stress used in &lt;strong&gt;figure 6D&lt;/strong&gt; to trigger Pab1 demixing is too mild to elicit Pab1-marked stress granules in wild type cells (&lt;strong&gt;figure 1A&lt;/strong&gt;). Moreover, while stress granules are easily observed, it is not clear that they are the physiologically functional species. Here, we make the case that perturbing demixing of Pab1 is sufficient to affect physiology. In fact, I favor the hypothesis that quinary assemblies and stress granules are related, but separable phenomena. Pab1 forms sedimentable quinary assemblies in the absence of visible focus formation. Conversely, HSP104 is an example of a protein that colocalizes with stress granules, but isn’t sedimentable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/CK_demix_then_SG_blueprint.png&quot; width=&quot;75%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;is-the-assembly-of-other-proteins-perturbed&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Is the assembly of other proteins perturbed?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yef3 is another protein that forms sedimentable species during mild stress conditions. &lt;strong&gt;Figure S5&lt;/strong&gt; indicates that demixing of Yef3 does not vary between P-domain mutants. However, it is possible that demixing of one of the other ~150 heat-assembling proteins is affected. At its core, this question is about the mechanism of formation of large cellular assemblies. Are all proteins demixing autonomously, or can one protein recruit another to these structures? Is RNA binding sufficient to recruit some proteins? Is recruitment stress specific?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-going-on-with-rna&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;What is going on with RNA?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right? In vitro we show the following: RNA is not necessary for Pab1 demixing (&lt;strong&gt;fig 2E&lt;/strong&gt;), RNA actually inhibits demixing (&lt;strong&gt;fig 2C&lt;/strong&gt;); and short poly(A) sequences are released during demixing (&lt;strong&gt;fig 2A&lt;/strong&gt;). One interpretation is that demixing is dominated by protein-protein interactions and these interactions are mutually exclusive with RNA binding. In vivo we show that heat-triggered sedimentation of Pab1 is RNase1 insensitive (&lt;strong&gt;fig 1B&lt;/strong&gt;). This result is consistent with the in vitro results, though other interpretations are possible. This model predicts that demixing of Pab1 and poly(A)-positive RNA are not mechanistically connected. I find this unintuitive, but testable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;you-speculate-about-pab1-as-a-translational-regulator-of-the-stress-response-how-much-is-speculation&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;You speculate about Pab1 as a translational regulator of the stress response. How much is speculation?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re curious about the mechanism by which Pab1 demixing affects stress tolerance, then come to my talk at &lt;strong&gt;ASBMB&lt;/strong&gt; “&lt;em&gt;Translation of heat shock proteins is regulated by poly(A)-binding protein assembly&lt;/em&gt;.” Its on &lt;strong&gt;Sunday April 23 2017&lt;/strong&gt; during the &lt;strong&gt;Protein folding, Aggregation, and Chaperones session&lt;/strong&gt;; or come see the poster later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;make-happy-yeast&quot;&gt;Make happy yeast:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pab1 is an essential gene with a role in many cellular processes. If one wishes to make mutations, delete then replace isn’t an option. Other work has successfully expressed Pab1 from a plasmid. However, cells are very sensitive to Pab1 expression levels – consistent with its known autoregulatory expression mechanism. My first attempt to modify the Pab1 P-domain was with a construct that replaced the native genomic 3’ UTR with a KanMX selectable marker. I also made the control strain with the same marker, but preserved P-domain. The control strain grew slowly and at 30°C and expressed Pab1 at ~20% the wild type. Reduced expression is problematic because demxing is concentration dependent; similarly, over-expression can lead to demixing artifacts. Worse, the proteome of this control strain resembled that of stressed wild type cells, including high chaperone expression. Ultimately, I developed the serial transformation strategy described in the methods (and another blog post). The resulting strains have no selectable markers, native 3’ UTRs, and no extra nucleotide scars. This manor of strain construction solved the reduced Pab1 expression and slow growth problems. Now, I am able to discern the relation of assembly and the stress response, without conflation of growth rate effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/CK_cool_yeast.png&quot; width=&quot;75%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>RNATagSeq: multiplexed library preparation for Illumina RNA sequencing</title>
   <link href="/protocols/protocol/rnatagseq-library-prep"/>
   <updated>2015-11-05T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>/protocols/protocol/rnatagseq-library-prep</id>
   <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;This protocol is for RNA sequencing (RNASeq) library preparation using the RNATagSeq method of Shishkin, et al. (2015). &lt;em&gt;Simultaneous generation of many RNA-seq libraries in a single reaction.&lt;/em&gt; Nature Methods, 12(4), 323–325. http://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.3313 (Broad institute).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The protocol is mildly adapted by Edward Wallace, mostly increasing some volumes to make SPRI bead handling easier. Applies to batches of 4 to 32 samples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The RNA-seqlopedia (http://rnaseq.uoregon.edu/) is a great background introduction to RNASeq.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reagents&quot;&gt;Reagents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wet-reagents&quot;&gt;Wet reagents&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Turbo DNase; Ambion/Applied Biosystems, Cat.# AM2239&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;FastAP Thermosensitive Alkaline Phosphatase; Thermo Scientific, Cat.# EF0651&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;RLT buffer (RNeasy Lysis Buffer); Qiagen, Cat.# 79216 (220mL)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;T4 RNA Ligase 1; 30,000U/mL (0.5mL) Cat.# MO437M and comes with the following:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;ATP(100mM) (make 10uL aliquots and store at -80°C, always use fresh aliquot)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;PEG8000,50% in water&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;DMSO (100%); Sigma, Cat.# D8418-50ML for Molecular Biology&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;RNase Inhibitor, Murine (40U/uL); NEB, Cat.# M0314S (3,000 units)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SUPERase-IN 20U/uL (Ambion; AM2694; 2500U)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AffinityScript Multiple Temperature cDNA Synthesis Kit, 50 reaction; Agilent, Cat.# 200436. includes the
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;dNTPs, 10x RT buffer, RNase Block Ribonuclease Inhibitor (40U/uL)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;10X AffinityScript RT buffer; Agilent, Cat.# 600100-52&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;RNA Clean &amp;amp; ConcentratorTM-5 columns; Zymo Research, Cat. #R1015 (50 preps)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SPRI beads:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;RNAClean XP beads; Agencourt/Beckman, Cat.# A63987 (40mL); (mix well, make 1.5mL and 0.5mL aliquots, store at 4 °C)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;For steps after cDNA synthesis, can use non-RNA certified, AMPure XP beads Cat.# A63881.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ribo-Zero:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Bacteria:
  Ribo-ZeroTM Magnetic Gold Kit (Bacteria); Epicentre/Illumina, Cat.# MRZMB126&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Human:
  Ribo-ZeroTM Magnetic Gold Kit (Human/Mouse/Rat); Epicentre/Illumina, Cat.# MRZG126&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Yeast: 
  Ribo-ZeroTM Magnetic Gold Kit (Yeast); Epicentre/Illumina, Cat.# MRZY1306&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sodium hydroxide solution (5M); Sigma-Aldrich, Cat.# 656046&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Glacial acetic acid (17.4M); Sigma-Aldrich, Cat.# ARK2183&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nuclease free water; Affymetrix Cat.#71786 100 ML or Ambion, Cat.# 4387936&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1x low TE (10mM Tris pH 8.0, 0.1mM EDTA); Affymetrix Cat.# 75793&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PfuUltra II Fusion HS DNA Polymerase; Agilent Cat.# 600670
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;10X PfuUltra II Reaction Buffer&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;platestubescaps&quot;&gt;Plates/Tubes/Caps:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flat PCR 12-cap strips, Optically clear; USA Scientific, Cat.# 1400-3120&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TempPlate No-skirt PCR Plates, 96 wells, 10 plates; USA Scientific, Cat.# 1402-9608&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.2 ml TempAssure PCR tube, attached flat cap, natural; USA Scientific, Cat.# 1402-8100&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;wide-orifice pipette tips for PEG-8000&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;instruments&quot;&gt;Instruments:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2100 Electrophoresis Bioanalyzer Instrument; Agilent, Cat.# G2939AA (at functional genomics core)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Agilent RNA 6000 Pico Kit; Agilent, Cat.# 5067-1513&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Agilent DNA HS Kit; Agilent, Cat.# 5067-4626&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;QIAvac 24 Plus Vacuum manifold (1-24 spin columns; Qiagen cat# 19413)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thermocycler&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;10uL, 100uL, 200uL pipettes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;96R Ring Magnet Plate. Agencourt Cat#. A29164 or Alpaqua Cat.# A001219&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;96-well Aluminum Cooler Blocks, Light Labs USA Cat#. A-7079&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This is not a protocol where you can cut corners. To save time and anguish, plan thoroughly, work cleanly, QC your samples and intermediate steps.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Label everything and lay out tubes neurotically to avoid pipette error.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Observe RNase-free sample prep, for steps 1-8, also neurotically. Clean your workspace and pipettes with 50% Ethanol and RNAse-Zap, use reserved RNase-free pipettes and RNAse-free (non-autoclaved) tips, ensure all tubes and reagents (including water) are RNase-free.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid DNA contamination, &lt;em&gt;especially from other sequencing libraries&lt;/em&gt; for steps 8+. Use filter tips for PCR reactions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Points where the in-process libraries may be frozen at -80 C while you pause, are indicated as &lt;em&gt;PAUSE POINT&lt;/em&gt;. Don’t take the risk of pausing elsewhere.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SPRI/XP beads take a bit of skill. “2x SPRI” refers to the ratio of beads to aqueous solution containing nucleic acids (NA); this ratio controls the size of NA retained (see http://core-genomics.blogspot.com/2012/04/how-do-spri-beads-work.html). Be patient; wait for binding and for magnetisation. Prepare fresh 80% ethanol solution every day or two; the concentration drifts over time due to evaporation (manufacturer recommends 70% EtOH). Some reactions (2nd ligation, step 11) happen on-bead so change the elution step. Manufacturer’s protocol with tweaks is below; practice SPRI extraction on a DNA ladder or RNA ladder and ensure full recovery.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add appropriate ratio of beads to sample in PCR tube, pipette up and down 10x gently.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Incubate beads and sample at room temperature  for 15min to bind NA.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Place on 96R plate magnet for 5min, until solution is clear&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pipette out and discard clear solution (save this for troubleshooting)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wash: Add 200uL fresh 80% EtOH without removing from magnet, incubate for 30sec, Pipette off clear solution.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Repeat 80% EtOH wash, use additional 10uL pipette to remove residual EtOH if necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Let air dry for 2min. Apparently, drying too short is bad because residual ethanol interferes with downstream reactions, and too long is bad because beads may crack and/or bind hydrophobically, overly strongly, to your NA.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Elute: remove from magnet, pipette 40uL water or low TE buffer onto beads, pipette up and down 10X, replace on magnet and wait 5min (this is easiest with at least 40uL, hellish with 10uL).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Unless otherwise specified, take clear liquid to new tube, carefully not disturbing beads.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For first ligation (step 5), set up RNA/barcoded adaptor in single tube or use the TempPlate No-skirt PCR Plates for batched samples (these rigid plates are easy to handle and can mix well by flicking by hand) – with a razor, cut a column (for 8 samples) or row (for 12 samples) and use as strip and cover with the Flat PCR 12-cap strips (these strips fit tightly on these plates and will not leak).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TempPlate No-skirt PCR Plates, and strips cut from them, are flexible and may spring up when caps are put on or off, flicking your sample across the bench. Avoid this by firmly seating plates/strips in a tube rack before manipulating  the caps.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Barcoded adaptors are listed in appendix, requiring 5’ Phosphate group (/5Phos/) and 3’ blocking spacer (/3SpC3/). The combination to use should be chosen carefully: plan a spreadsheet listing the sample name, conditions, and which RNAtag adaptor (step 3) and P7 adaptor (step 14/17, PCR after pooling) will be used. In each set of sequencing libraries combined on an Illumina sequencing run, there must be at least 3 distinct nt in all of the initial 4 nt of the sequenced adaptor for the sequencing machine to recognize clusters properly. (e.g. ATTA, GCAC, CAGT work, ATTA, GTAC, CTGT don’t due to the common T.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Control oligos:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tag33FAM&lt;br /&gt;
  5’ - /5Phos/AG AAC GAT TAG ATC GGA AGA GCG TCG TGT A/36-FAM/ - 3’&lt;br /&gt;
  is a fluorescent positive control oligo for first ligation and sample pooling. Use in place of a barcoded adaptor, for one sample, in first ligation, step 5. Success is indicated if fluorescence appears in 200-500nt smear:&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;TagDNA+&lt;br /&gt;
  5’-TAC ACG ACG CTC TTC CGA TCT TCA GTC AGT ATG TAC GCG TAG CGC AGC GAG CGG CGG GTG GCC ACG TCG CGG CAC ACG CGG ATG GAC AGG ATC GGG CCG GCG GGC AGG AAC TTC TCG TAG AGC ATG GCC TCG GTC ACG TCG GCG TGC AGG TCG CCC ACG TAG AGC GAG GCC AGC GGG TAC CCC GGG CCG CTG GCG TTC AT - 3’&lt;br /&gt;
  is a 200bp oligo as positive control for 2nd ligation through PCR. Use 1.25uM (0.5uL of 100uM stock) in place of cDNA in control reaction in step 11. Its 3’ end resembles a cDNA product for a library with Tag barcode CTGACTGA (distinct from Tag1-32, Tag33FAM), and the insert is “random” (elephant PABP 1st exon).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;procedure&quot;&gt;Procedure:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Control quality and quantity of RNA with Agilent Bioanalyzer
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Check RNA quality by running on the Agilent Bioanalyzer&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Place 0.5-5 ug of total RNA in a tube. For large numbers of samples, the input per sample could be reduced as to not exceed the maximum input of RiboZero (5ug) at step 5. Since about 25% of the input remains prior to adaptor ligation, less than 20ug total RNA per pool (end of step 4) is recommended. For smaller number of samples, higher input is recommended to ensure sufficient material remains after rRNA depletion.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Increase the volume to 30uL with Nuclease free water&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 2uL of SUPERase-IN (20U/uL)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Final total volume = 32uL (25ng/uL)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Continue to next step or freeze at -80C until ready to process samples&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PAUSE POINT&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fragment RNA using 2x FastAP buffer
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 8 uL of 10X FastAP buffer to 32 uL RNA from step 1 (up to 1 ug) and mix well.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Incubate on &lt;em&gt;preheated&lt;/em&gt; thermal cycler for 3 min at 94°C.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If RNA is partially degraded (RIN&amp;lt;7), fragment 3 min at 92°C, prevents over-fragmenting samples.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Place on cold block on ice.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Digest DNA and repair RNA: Combination DNase/FastAP treatment
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Make a DNase/FastAP master mix, 40uL per sample:&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;table&gt;
          &lt;thead&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
              &lt;th&gt;Reagent (for 2X FastAP master)&lt;/th&gt;
              &lt;th&gt;Amount&lt;/th&gt;
              &lt;th&gt;Final&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
          &lt;/thead&gt;
          &lt;tbody&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;nuclease-free water&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;10 uL&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;RNase Inhibitor, Murine (40U/uL)&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;2 uL&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;20U&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;TURBO DNase (2U/uL)&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;8 uL&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;16U&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;FastAP (1U/uL)&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;20 uL&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;20U&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
          &lt;/tbody&gt;
          &lt;tbody&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;Total&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;40 uL&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;2X&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
          &lt;/tbody&gt;
        &lt;/table&gt;

        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Mix well&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Aliquot 40 uL into each tube/well with the 40uL of fragmented RNA from step 1.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mix well&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Incubate on preheated thermal cycler for 30 min at 37°C&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cleanup (2x SPRI) to remove enzymes and reaction buffer
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 2.0x reaction volume of Agencourt RNAClean XP beads (160 uL) and  capture RNA on beads:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Incubate at room temperature for 15min to bind RNA&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Place on magnet for 5min, until solution is clear&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Pipette out and discard clear solution&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Add 200uL fresh 80% EtOH without removing from magnet, incubate for 30sec, Pipette off supernatant.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Repeat 80% EtOH wash. Let air dry for 2min&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Elute off beads with 24 uL nuclease free water&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Take 5 uL of each sample and proceed to 1st ligation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;QC: Save 1.2 uL from remaining RNA before addition of SUPERase-IN&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Run 11 random samplings on Agilent RNA pico chip to check the fragmentation profile of each batch of 32&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 1uL SUPERase-IN (20U/uL) to the remaining material and store at -80°C.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;this can be used as backup if it is necessary to repeat process&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PAUSE POINT&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ligate 3’ barcoded Adaptor: First Ligation (ssRNA/ssDNA)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 1 uL of barcoded RNATag adaptor (100 pmole = 1 uL of 100 uM) to 5 uL of dephosphorylated RNA&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Heat at 70°C for 2 min, place in cold block on ice&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Set up First Ligation master mix below
  NOTE:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;All reagents except enzymes (-20°C ) should be stored at -80°C in single use aliquots and brought to room temp just before use&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Make up mix &lt;em&gt;at room temp&lt;/em&gt; so the reagents don’t start precipitating when combined (if DMSO is added directly into cold buffer it will precipitate)&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Pipette very slowly with wide-opening/cut tips for accurate aspiration of PEG (very viscous)&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;When setting up mix for multiple reactions include 25% extra to account for pipetting error due to the viscosity&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;table&gt;
              &lt;thead&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                  &lt;th&gt;Reagent (for Ligation master)&lt;/th&gt;
                  &lt;th&gt;1 rxn&lt;/th&gt;
                  &lt;th&gt;40 rxns&lt;/th&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
              &lt;/thead&gt;
              &lt;tbody&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;10× T4 RNA Ligase Buffer&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;2 uL&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;80 uL&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;DMSO (100%)&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;1.8 uL&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;72 uL&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;ATP (100 mM)&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;0.2 uL&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;8 uL&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;PEG 8000 (50%)&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;8 uL&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;320 uL&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;RNase inhibitor, Murine (40U/uL)&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;0.3 uL&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;12 uL&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
              &lt;/tbody&gt;
              &lt;tbody&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;Total&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;12.3 uL&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;492 uL&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
              &lt;/tbody&gt;
            &lt;/table&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Mix really well by extensive vortexing tube since the solution is very viscous, then spin down briefly in microfuge&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 12.3 uL of ligation master mix to each tube/well containing 6 uL denatured RNA + adaptor.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 1.8 uL of T4 RNA Ligase 1 (30,000U/mL) to each tube/well. 20.1 uL reaction volume total.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mix well &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; times; mix by flicking since the solution is very viscous&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Incubate at 22°C (room temp) for 1 hour 30 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pool barcoded RNA: RLT buffer + Zymo column&lt;br /&gt;
 NOTE: At this point, multiple samples with distinct RNAtag adaptors will be pooled on the same spin column. Do not exceed 5ug RNA per pool, the maximum binding capacity of columns. Attempt to normalize the amounts (using your QC in step 4, or even 1) based on the amount of non-ribosomal RNA in each pool, or your other needs.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 60 uL of RLT buffer to each sample to inhibit ligase, and mix well (80 uL total)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pooling and clean up using Zymo Clean &amp;amp; ConcentratorTM-5 column - follow manufacturer’s &lt;em&gt;200nt&lt;/em&gt; cut off protocol:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Add 2x reaction vol (160 uL=2x 80 uL) of 1:1 binding buffer: EtOH (100%) / reaction&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Carefully add reactions to be pooled to a single Zymo column.&lt;br /&gt;
  NOTE: When pooling &amp;gt;700 uL onto Zymo column use a vacuum manifold then proceed to centrifugation steps according to the manual&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Wash and spin 1 min 12,000 g, then discard flow-through, once with 400 uL RNA Prep buffer, once with 800 uL RNA Wash buffer, once with 400uL Wash buffer, spin another 1min with no buffer.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Elute 2 times with 16 uL nuclease free water for a total volume of 32 uL&lt;br /&gt;
  NOTE: 2 elutions help improve recovery/yield of RNA&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Save 2 uL for QC-Run on Agilent RNA pico chip to check quantity and fragmentation profile&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PAUSE POINT&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deplete ribosomal RNA with RiboZero (optional)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;See Manufacturer’s instructions Quick Protocol for Ribo-ZeroTM&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;End with 1.8x SPRI cleanup, elute into 14 uL water, save 2 uL for QC&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Synthesize First Strand cDNA
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Take 12 uL rRNA depleted RNA (use all the material from Ribo-Zero)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 2 uL (50 pmoles) of AR2 primer (25 uM)
   5’-TAC ACG ACG CTC TTC CGA T-3’ AR2, 53% GC, 19bp.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mix well&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Heat the mixture to 70°C for 2 min and immediately place on cold block on ice&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Make RT master mix
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Add in order on ice&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;table&gt;
              &lt;thead&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                  &lt;th&gt;Reagent (for RT master)&lt;/th&gt;
                  &lt;th&gt;1 rxn&lt;/th&gt;
                  &lt;th&gt;2.5 rxns&lt;/th&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
              &lt;/thead&gt;
              &lt;tbody&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;10× AffinityScript RT Buffer&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;2   uL&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;5   uL&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;DTT (0.1M)&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;2   uL&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;5   uL&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;25mM dNTP Mix (25mM each)&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;0.8 uL&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;2   uL&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;RNase inhibitor, murine (40U/uL)&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;0.4 uL&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;1   uL&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
              &lt;/tbody&gt;
              &lt;tbody&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;Total&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;5.2 uL&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;13   uL&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
              &lt;/tbody&gt;
            &lt;/table&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Mix well&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 5.2 uL of RT mix to the 14 uL rRNA depleted RNA + AR2 RTprimer on ice&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 0.8 uL of AffinityScript RT Enzyme&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mix well and spin for 5 sec&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Place in &lt;em&gt;preheated&lt;/em&gt; (55 °C) incubator or thermocycler. Incubate at 55 °C for 55 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Degrade RNA after reverse transcription&lt;br /&gt;
 NOTE: make fresh working stock solutions of NaOH and Acetic Acid
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 10% reaction vol. of 1M NaOH (2 uL) to each reaction&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Incubate at 70 °C for 12 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Neutralize with 4 uL of 0.5M Acetic Acid; mix well&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Total volume = 26 uL&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cleanup reverse transcription (2x SPRI) to remove enzyme, primers, and reaction buffer
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 14 uL of sterile water to each reaction for a final volume of 40 uL&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Transfer to new tubes (NaOH may start degrading tubes)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 2x reaction volume SPRI beads (80uL) to the sample in new tubes, and mix up/down 10x&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Incubate at room temperature for 15min&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Place on magnet for 5 min or until solution is clear&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pipette out and discard clear solution&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wash: Add 200 uL fresh 80% EtOH without removing from magnet and incubate for 30 sec. Pipette off and discard the EtOH.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Repeat 80% EtOH wash, and let air dry for 3min, remove from magnet.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 5 uL RNase/DNase free water to beads – &lt;em&gt;KEEP BEADS AND TUBES, do not transfer, do not pause&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ligate 3’ Universal Adaptor: Second Ligation (ssDNA/ssDNA) with beads&lt;br /&gt;
NOTE: 3Tr3 adaptor: 5’-/5Phos/AGA TCG GAA GAG CAC ACG TCT G-/3SpC3/ 3’, 55% GC, 22bp, 5’-Phos and 3’-C3 spacer (or ddC, or dye). Make 40 uM stock.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 2 uL (80 pmoles) of 3Tr3 adaptor to cDNA&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Heat at 75°C for 3 min; Place on cold block on ice&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Make ligation reaction master mix (can be prepared ahead of time, at RT):&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2nd Ligation Master Mix:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Mix in order&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;table&gt;
              &lt;thead&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                  &lt;th&gt;Reagent (for Ligation 2 master)&lt;/th&gt;
                  &lt;th&gt;1 rxn&lt;/th&gt;
                  &lt;th&gt;2.5 rxns&lt;/th&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
              &lt;/thead&gt;
              &lt;tbody&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;10× T4 RNA Ligase Buffer&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;2 uL&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;5   uL&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;DMSO (100%)&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;0.8 uL&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;2   uL&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;ATP (100 mM)&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;0.2 uL&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;0.5 uL&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;PEG 8000 (50%)&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;8.5 uL&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;21.3 uL&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;T4 RNA Ligase 1 (30,000U/mL)&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;1.5 uL&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;3.8 uL&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
              &lt;/tbody&gt;
              &lt;tbody&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;Total&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;13.0 uL&lt;/td&gt;
                  &lt;td&gt;32.6 uL&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
              &lt;/tbody&gt;
            &lt;/table&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Mix really well by extensive vortexing tube since the solution is very viscous&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Spin down briefly in microfuge&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Swirl the 7uL cDNA/beads/water with pipet tip, THEN add 13 uL ligation 2 master mix.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mix well by pipetting up and down 20x or cap tubes and flick several times; solution is viscous&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Quick spin (low speed centrifuge, to get everything to bottom of tube)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Incubate overnight at 22 °C&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cleanup (2x SPRI) to remove adaptors
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 2x reaction volume SPRI beads (80uL) to the sample in new tubes, and mix up/down 10x&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Incubate at room temperature for 15min&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Place on magnet for 5 min or until solution is clear&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pipette out and discard clear solution&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wash: Add 200 uL fresh 80% EtOH without removing from magnet and incubate for 30 sec. Pipette off discard the EtOH.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Repeat 80% EtOH wash, and let air dry for 3min&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Elute DNA by adding 30 uL RNase/DNase free water, transfer to new tube.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2nd Cleanup (1.5x SPRI) to remove the remaining adaptors
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 1.5x reaction volume SPRI beads (45 uL) to the sample in new tubes, and mix up/down 10x&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Incubate at room temperature for 15min&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Place on magnet for 5 min or until solution is clear&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pipette out and discard clear solution&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wash: Add 200 uL fresh 80% EtOH without removing from magnet and incubate for 30 sec. Pipette off and discard the EtOH.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Repeat 80% EtOH wash, and let air dry for 3min&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Elute DNA by adding 25 uL RNase/DNase free water, transfer to new tube.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PAUSE POINT&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TEST PCR Amplification to determine final cycle number&lt;br /&gt;
NOTE: P5 primer: P5_RNATag, 5’-AAT GAT ACG GCG ACC ACC GAG ATC TAC ACT CTT TCC CTA CAC GAC GCT CTT CCG ATC T-3’, 52% GC, 58bp; standard DNA oligo. Make 100uM stock and 12.5uM working stock.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Set up a test PCR using 5 uL of ss cDNA sample and 9-12 cycles of PCR (based on experience with pool of 16 reactions, each starting with ~400ng total RNA)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Include a negative control (water) for each primer set&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Make PCR Master Mix (4 rxns=2 libraries, +ve ctrl, -ve ctrl):
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Add in order:&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;

        &lt;table&gt;
          &lt;thead&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
              &lt;th&gt;Reagent (for PCR master mix)&lt;/th&gt;
              &lt;th&gt;1 rxn&lt;/th&gt;
              &lt;th&gt;4 rxns&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
          &lt;/thead&gt;
          &lt;tbody&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;Water, PCR-clean&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;14.3 uL&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;57.2 uL&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;10X Pfu Ultra II Buffer&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;2.5 uL&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;10   uL&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;dNTP mix (10mM each)&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;0.7 uL&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;2.8 uL&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;P5 primer (P5_RNATag, 12.5 uM)&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;1   uL&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;4   uL&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
          &lt;/tbody&gt;
          &lt;tbody&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;Total&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;18.5 uL&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;74   uL&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
          &lt;/tbody&gt;
        &lt;/table&gt;

        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Mix well&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Aliquot 18.5 uL / sample into PCR tubes&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 1 uL of appropriate P7 index primer to each well&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 5 uL of ss cDNA from step 11, or water (for negative control)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 0.5 uL of Pfu Ultra II Polymerase.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mix well and aliquot 8 ul into each of 3 tubes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Place each in a thermal cycler with cycling conditions:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;start: 98°C, 3min&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;cycle: 9, 12, 15 cycles (for test PCR)
  98°C, 30sec; 55°C, 30sec; 70°C, 30sec&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;end: 70°C, 2min; 4°C, hold&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cleanup (1.5x SPRI) to remove reaction buffer and PCR primers:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;increase reaction to 40uL with sterile water&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 1.5x reaction volume SPRI beads (60 uL) to the sample in new tubes, and mix up/down 10x&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Incubate at room temperature for 15min&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Place on magnet for 5 min or until solution is clear&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pipette out and discard clear solution&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wash: Add 200 uL fresh 80% EtOH without removing from magnet and incubate for 30 sec. Pipette off and discard the EtOH.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Repeat 80% EtOH wash, and let air dry for 3min&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Elute off beads with 10 uL 1x low TE (10 mM Tris, 0.1M EDTA)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;QC test PCR amplification on Agilent DNA HS chip
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Based on test results change the cycle number, if necessary, and set up more reactions to provide enough material to send for sequencing&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;UChicago functional genomics core asks for ~15 uL of 10 nM library; aim for at least 25 uL = 0.25 pmol = 60 ng of 400nt dsDNA (~250 kDa).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To pass QC, library should have smooth profile 200-500nt long; visible single bands, or a “shoulder” of larger products, indicate PCR artefacts.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PAUSE POINT&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PCR for Sequencing library
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Choose the optimal PCR cycle # based on Bioanalyzer QC of test (step 15).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Include a negative control (water) for each primer set&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Make PCR Master Mix (3 rxns=2 libraries, half size +ve ctrl, half size -ve ctrl):
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Add in order:&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;

        &lt;table&gt;
          &lt;thead&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
              &lt;th&gt;Reagent (for PCR master mix)&lt;/th&gt;
              &lt;th&gt;1 rxn&lt;/th&gt;
              &lt;th&gt;3 rxns&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
          &lt;/thead&gt;
          &lt;tbody&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;Water, PCR-clean&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;28.6 uL&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;85.8 uL&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;10X Pfu Ultra II Buffer&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;5   uL&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;15   uL&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;dNTP mix (10mM each)&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;1.4 uL&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;4.2 uL&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;P5 primer (P5_RNATag, 12.5 uM)&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;2   uL&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;6   uL&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
          &lt;/tbody&gt;
          &lt;tbody&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;Total&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;37   uL&lt;/td&gt;
              &lt;td&gt;111   uL&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
          &lt;/tbody&gt;
        &lt;/table&gt;

        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Mix well&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Aliquot 37 uL / sample into PCR tubes&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 2 uL of appropriate P7 index primer to each well&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 10 uL of ss cDNA from step 11, or water (for negative control)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 1 uL of Pfu Ultra II Polymerase.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mix well and aliquot 10 ul into each of 5 wells of a 96-well plate (amplification is apparently more robust in smaller volumes), cap.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Place each in a thermal cycler with the cycling conditions:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;start: 98°C, 3min&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;cycle: # determined from test PCR
  98°C, 30sec; 55°C, 30sec; 70°C, 30sec&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;end: 70°C, 2min; 4°C, hold&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cleanup (1.5x SPRI) to remove reaction buffer and PCR primers:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pool PCR reaction (50 uL)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 1.5x reaction volume SPRI beads (75 uL) to the sample in new tubes, and mix up/down 10x&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Incubate at room temperature for 15min&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Place on magnet for 5 min or until solution is clear&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pipette out and discard clear solution&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wash: Add 200 uL fresh 80% EtOH without removing from magnet and incubate for 30 sec. Pipette off and discard the EtOH.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Repeat 80% EtOH wash, and let air dry for 3min&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Elute off beads with 50 uL water and transfer to new tubes.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Final Cleanup (0.8x SPRI) to remove remaining PCR primers:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add 0.8x reaction volume SPRI beads (40 uL) to the sample in new tubes, and mix up/down 10x&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Incubate at room temperature for 15min&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Place on magnet for 5 min or until solution is clear&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pipette out and discard clear solution&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wash: Add 200 uL fresh 80% EtOH without removing from magnet and incubate for 30 sec. Pipette off and discard the EtOH.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Repeat 80% EtOH wash, and let air dry for 3min&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Elute off beads with 25 uL 1x low TE (10 mM Tris, 0.1M EDTA)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Proceed to sequence
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Check quantity/quality on Bioanalyzer with Agilent DNA HS chip as step 16.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Submit to genomics core for sequencing.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If desired to combine multiple libraries PCR’d separately, they must have different barcoded P7 primers. Amounts of sequenceable material must be carefully measured to ensure even coverage across libraries, e.g. with the KAPA biosystems kit (Cat. # KK4824). The genomics core can do this for a fee.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;appendix-barcode-tag-oligos&quot;&gt;Appendix: Barcode Tag Oligos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;| id       | Well | barcode sequence (5'-3') | oligo sequence                 | 8 base Barcode Read + T | IDTorder                                               | 
|----------|------|--------------------------|--------------------------------|-------------------------|--------------------------------------------------------| 
| Tag01    | A1   | CCCGTCTT                 | ACCCGTCTTAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | AAGACGGGT               | /5Phos/ACC CGT CTT AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag02    | A2   | CGGCACTT                 | ACGGCACTTAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | AAGTGCCGT               | /5Phos/ACG GCA CTT AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag03    | A3   | ACATTATT                 | AACATTATTAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | AATAATGTT               | /5Phos/AAC ATT ATT AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag04    | A4   | GAGATTGT                 | AGAGATTGTAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | ACAATCTCT               | /5Phos/AGA GAT TGT AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag05    | A5   | GGTCCTCT                 | AGGTCCTCTAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | AGAGGACCT               | /5Phos/AGG TCC TCT AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag06    | A6   | CTCTAACT                 | ACTCTAACTAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | AGTTAGAGT               | /5Phos/ACT CTA ACT AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag07    | A7   | AGAATTAT                 | AAGAATTATAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | ATAATTCTT               | /5Phos/AAG AAT TAT AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag08    | A8   | TACAACAT                 | ATACAACATAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | ATGTTGTAT               | /5Phos/ATA CAA CAT AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag09    | C1   | AAGTGTTG                 | AAAGTGTTGAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | CAACACTTT               | /5Phos/AAA GTG TTG AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag10    | C2   | ATCACTTG                 | AATCACTTGAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | CAAGTGATT               | /5Phos/AAT CAC TTG AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag11    | C3   | TCATCGTG                 | ATCATCGTGAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | CACGATGAT               | /5Phos/ATC ATC GTG AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag12    | C4   | TACAGATG                 | ATACAGATGAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | CATCTGTAT               | /5Phos/ATA CAG ATG AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag13    | C5   | TCCCGCGG                 | ATCCCGCGGAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | CCGCGGGAT               | /5Phos/ATC CCG CGG AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag14    | C6   | CCAAGTCG                 | ACCAAGTCGAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | CGACTTGGT               | /5Phos/ACC AAG TCG AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag15    | C7   | CTGGATCG                 | ACTGGATCGAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | CGATCCAGT               | /5Phos/ACT GGA TCG AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag16    | C8   | GTCTGGCG                 | AGTCTGGCGAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | CGCCAGACT               | /5Phos/AGT CTG GCG AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag17    | E1   | TTACCACG                 | ATTACCACGAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | CGTGGTAAT               | /5Phos/ATT ACC ACG AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag18    | E2   | TGAACCAG                 | ATGAACCAGAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | CTGGTTCAT               | /5Phos/ATG AAC CAG AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag19    | E3   | CCCTACAG                 | ACCCTACAGAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | CTGTAGGGT               | /5Phos/ACC CTA CAG AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag20    | E4   | GGCCCAAG                 | AGGCCCAAGAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | CTTGGGCCT               | /5Phos/AGG CCC AAG AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag21    | E5   | GAGCCATC                 | AGAGCCATCAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | GATGGCTCT               | /5Phos/AGA GCC ATC AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag22    | E6   | GTAACTGC                 | AGTAACTGCAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | GCAGTTACT               | /5Phos/AGT AAC TGC AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag23    | E7   | CGGAGGGC                 | ACGGAGGGCAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | GCCCTCCGT               | /5Phos/ACG GAG GGC AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag24    | E8   | CCCTCGGC                 | ACCCTCGGCAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | GCCGAGGGT               | /5Phos/ACC CTC GGC AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag25    | G1   | CAACTCGC                 | ACAACTCGCAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | GCGAGTTGT               | /5Phos/ACA ACT CGC AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag26    | G2   | TACCGGCC                 | ATACCGGCCAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | GGCCGGTAT               | /5Phos/ATA CCG GCC AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag27    | G3   | CCGGTACC                 | ACCGGTACCAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | GGTACCGGT               | /5Phos/ACC GGT ACC AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag28    | G4   | CTCGGTAC                 | ACTCGGTACAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | GTACCGAGT               | /5Phos/ACT CGG TAC AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag29    | G5   | ATATGGAC                 | AATATGGACAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | GTCCATATT               | /5Phos/AAT ATG GAC AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag30    | G6   | TGGGAGAC                 | ATGGGAGACAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | GTCTCCCAT               | /5Phos/ATG GGA GAC AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag31    | G7   | GCAGCCAC                 | AGCAGCCACAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | GTGGCTGCT               | /5Phos/AGC AGC CAC AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
| Tag32    | G8   | TTTCTAAC                 | ATTTCTAACAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | GTTAGAAAT               | /5Phos/ATT TCT AAC AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/3SpC3/  | 
|          |      |                          |                                |                         |                                                        | 
| Tag33FAM | H12  | GAACGATT                 | AGAACGATTAGATCGGAAGAGCGTCGTGTA | AATCGTTCT               | /5Phos/AGA ACG ATT AGA TCG GAA GAG CGT CGT GTA/36-FAM/ | 
|          |      |                          |                                |                         |                                                        | 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: 3Tr3 primer (/5Phos/AGA TCG GAA GAG CAC ACG TCT G/3SpC3/) is in well A12 of the IDT plate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;appendix-p7-bindex-oligos&quot;&gt;Appendix: P7 Bindex Oligos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;| Name   | P7 Enrichment Primer Sequence (5' --&amp;gt; 3') with barcode             | barcodes (BC) | BC READ (reverse complement) | 
|--------|--------------------------------------------------------------------|---------------|------------------------------| 
| P7_B1  | CAAGCAGAAGACGGCATACGAGATTCGTGTGCGTGACTGGAGTTCAGACGTGTGCTCTTCCGATCT | TCGTGTGC      | GCACACGA                     | 
| P7_B2  | CAAGCAGAAGACGGCATACGAGATTCGCCAGAGTGACTGGAGTTCAGACGTGTGCTCTTCCGATCT | TCGCCAGA      | TCTGGCGA                     | 
| P7_B3  | CAAGCAGAAGACGGCATACGAGATTCGCTATGGTGACTGGAGTTCAGACGTGTGCTCTTCCGATCT | TCGCTATG      | CATAGCGA                     | 
| P7_B4  | CAAGCAGAAGACGGCATACGAGATGGCTCCTGGTGACTGGAGTTCAGACGTGTGCTCTTCCGATCT | GGCTCCTG      | CAGGAGCC                     | 
| P7_B5  | CAAGCAGAAGACGGCATACGAGATATCCGACAGTGACTGGAGTTCAGACGTGTGCTCTTCCGATCT | ATCCGACA      | TGTCGGAT                     | 
| P7_B6  | CAAGCAGAAGACGGCATACGAGATAACATAATGTGACTGGAGTTCAGACGTGTGCTCTTCCGATCT | AACATAAT      | ATTATGTT                     | 
| P7_B7  | CAAGCAGAAGACGGCATACGAGATATGGTAGGGTGACTGGAGTTCAGACGTGTGCTCTTCCGATCT | ATGGTAGG      | CCTACCAT                     | 
| P7_B8  | CAAGCAGAAGACGGCATACGAGATGCTAAGTAGTGACTGGAGTTCAGACGTGTGCTCTTCCGATCT | GCTAAGTA      | TACTTAGC                     | 
| P7_B9  | CAAGCAGAAGACGGCATACGAGATGTTCCAACGTGACTGGAGTTCAGACGTGTGCTCTTCCGATCT | GTTCCAAC      | GTTGGAAC                     | 
| P7_B10 | CAAGCAGAAGACGGCATACGAGATTCCAAGGAGTGACTGGAGTTCAGACGTGTGCTCTTCCGATCT | TCCAAGGA      | TCCTTGGA                     | 
| P7_B11 | CAAGCAGAAGACGGCATACGAGATCAAGGTTGGTGACTGGAGTTCAGACGTGTGCTCTTCCGATCT | CAAGGTTG      | CAACCTTG                     | 
| P7_B12 | CAAGCAGAAGACGGCATACGAGATAGGTTCCTGTGACTGGAGTTCAGACGTGTGCTCTTCCGATCT | AGGTTCCT      | AGGAACCT                     | 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Yeast total RNA isolation protocol</title>
   <link href="/protocols/protocol/yeast-rna-isolation"/>
   <updated>2015-10-30T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>/protocols/protocol/yeast-rna-isolation</id>
   <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;This is a yeast total RNA isolation protocol that works very well and reliably. It takes a couple of hours.
We have also had success with the Zymo Direct-Zol columns which are faster but can be less clean if overloaded.
For general advice working with RNA consult &lt;em&gt;RNA: A Laboratory Manual&lt;/em&gt;, from Cold Spring Harbor Press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use RNase-free water, reagents, and equipment throughout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grow up 5ml liquid yeast culture to OD 2.0 for lots of RNA (or as desired). Spin at 3000g for 4min
at room temperature. Remove supernatant and resuspend pellet in
500ul RNA lysis buffer (10mM Tris-HCl pH8.5, 5mM
EDTA, 2% SDS, 2% stock 2-mercaptoethanol).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Transfer liquid to 1.5ml tube and put on heat block at 83 with
450rpm mixing for 20mins (to disrupt cells and denature proteins).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spin down for 5mins at 12,000g.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Take supernatant into new tube and add 550 ul of
Phenol pH8. Vortex for 15 mins&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spin down for 2mins at 12,000g. There should be a lower phenol
phase, a cloudy interphase, and an upper aqueous phase: RNA
partitions mostly into the upper phase. Transfer upper aqueous phase
(roughly 200 ul ) to new 1.5ml tube (labeled
tube N). Add 250 ul RNA lysis buffer to previous
tube (labeled tube P) and vortex tube P for 5mins.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add 250 ul chloroform to tube P to suck off phenol
from water phase (This completes a phenol:chloroform extraction of
RNA from the original sample). Vortex for 3 mins, then spin 2mins at
12,000g and transfer aqueous phase from tube P to tube N. Discard
tube P.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A second phenol extraction: add 550 ul phenol to
tube N. Vortex 5mins, spin 2mins at 12,000g.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Transfer aqueous phase to another 1.5ml tube, discard tube N. Add
550 ul phenol:chloroform pH4.5. Vortex 3mins, then
spin 2mins at 12,000g.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Transfer 450 ul aqueous phase to yet another 1.5ml
tube, add 200 ul of 0.6M Sodium acetate pH4.5, mix
by flicking, and spin briefly. Add 600  ul of
phenol:chloroform pH4.5. Vortex 5mins, then spin 2 mins at 12,000g.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Transfer 350 ul aqueous phase to a fresh 1.5ml tube,
add 30  ul 5M Ammonium acetate and 1.1ml ethanol.
Mix well, and precipitate at -80 for 20mins. The sample may be left
for longer, for example overnight, at this point if a pause
is desired.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Remove the sample from freezer. Cold spin (4) for 15 mins
at 12,000g.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thoroughly remove ethanol from pellet, and add 700 ul
80% ethanol. Cold spin (4C) for 2 minutes at 12,000g. Repeat the
ethanol wash and cold spin. This removes all traces of salt,
SDS, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dry pellets thoroughly, i.e., pipette off ethanol, removing
all liquid. If necessary, dry with the tubes open on a 37 heat block
(if the RNA sample is pure, this should not degrade the RNA).
Resuspend pellet in 50  ul H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To check the quality of the RNA, pour a 1% agarose gel on RNA-free
equipment, and run using RNA loading dye supplied with a ladder (RiboRuler High Range, 
ThermoFisher #SM1821, or ssRNA Ladder, NEB #N0362S). Heat loading dye and
H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O to 95 for 5 minutes, and then cool, to reduce the possibility
of contamination. Mix 1 ul sample, 5 ul H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O, and 6 ul 2X loading dye for
each well. You should see clear ~4000nt and ~2000 nt bands corresponding to 
ribosomal RNA (25S/18S), also a blur at ~80nt for tRNA, and good gels 
show the 5S and 5.8S rRNAs at ~150nt.
Perform a 2X serial dilution of the sample for more
precise quantification, or run on Agilent Bioanalyzer RNA Nano chip.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To find out how much sample is lost in the first centrifugation,
resuspend pellet in 500 ul of RNA lysis buffer, and
repeat 3 previous steps. Label tube distinctly and proceed in
parallel with the main sample. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Sucrose gradient protocol for polysome profiles</title>
   <link href="/protocols/protocol/sucrose-gradient"/>
   <updated>2015-10-30T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>/protocols/protocol/sucrose-gradient</id>
   <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;This protocol is for polysome fractionation by sucrose gradient, to view
translational status of cells and ribosome-association of mRNAs and
proteins, using the BioComp gradient station
(http://www.biocompinstruments.com/). It’s based on the BioComp
instructions, with help from Wesley Clark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the BioComp instruction book for more details of gradient station 
operation, especially for troubleshooting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;components&quot;&gt;Components&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wet-ingredients&quot;&gt;Wet ingredients&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sample: 100-500 ul cell lysate, with assembled
polysomes, at OD260 ~ 100.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mammalian Polysome gradient buffer: 100mM KCl, 7.5mM MgCl2, 5mM
Tris-HCl pH7.5, or,&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yeast Polysome gradient buffer: 140mM KCl, 5mM MgCl2, 5mM Tris-HCl pH7.5
(NOTE: Can adjust salt, Mg, pH, etc; common additions are cycloheximide to
freeze ribosomes in place, heparin to reduce nonspecific RNA-protein binding and
inhibit RNase, DTT as reducing agent, RNase inhibitors. I’ve made good
polysome gradients without any of these at 2-10mM MgCl2, pH 6.5-7.5. Degraded
DTT is really bad as it absorbs over the RNA spectrum.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;50% Sucrose buffer: 0.5g/ml sucrose in polysome gradient buffer, filter sterilized.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;10% Sucrose buffer: 0.1g/ml sucrose in polysome gradient buffer, filter sterilized.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dry-ingredients&quot;&gt;Dry ingredients&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;BioComp Instruments gradient station.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Beckman Coulter S-rated ultracentrifuge, e.g. Optima XP-100.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Beckman SW28 rotor and SW28.1 (or SW28) tube buckets, kept in cold room. Rotor
must be placed only on rotor-holding platform, do not scratch speed ring on bottom.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Seton open-top polyclear centrifuge tubes SW28.1 (part.no 7042). Alternatively, 
SW28 (part.no 7052); SW28 are wider and slightly shorter.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prepare-gradients&quot;&gt;Prepare gradients&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Layer sucrose into centrifuge tube: place a polyclear centrifuge tube in the
marker block. Pour 10% sucrose buffer into the tube up to the top of the marker
block (roughly 10ml for SW28.1 / 19.5ml for SW28). Load 50% sucrose buffer into
a 50ml Luer-lok syringe with a layering cannula (BioComp 106-211) attached; with
the needle pointing upwards, expel air from the needle. Quickly and smoothly
invert the syringe so the needle is in the bottom centre of the half-filled
centrifuge tube. Slowly layer 50% sucrose buffer at the bottom of the tube until
the top of the meniscus is at the top of the tube (roughly 10ml; 19ml for SW28),
and carefully remove needle from tube. Place the capillary cap on top of the
tube, ensuring tube is sealed round edges of cap. Repeat for desired number of
tubes (2, 4 or 6 total), and place filled tubes in magnetic tube rack.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level the gradient maker platform on the gradient station: turn
gradient-maker on, choose GMST menu option. The machine will prompt you to level
the gradient-making platform. Place a bubble level on the platform with axis
perpendicular to the side plate of the machine and use the UP and DOWN menu
options to level the platform (the machine should already be level front to
back); press DONE.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Make gradients: place magnetic tube rack on gradient-making platform. Select
GRAD option to arrive at gradient menu. The first time, go to LIST and choose
the SW28.1 (or SW28) rotor option. Press DOWN until arriving at the 10-50% sucrose 
gradient option, and press USE. If the machine was used for 10-50% sucrose gradient
immediately previously, simply select LAST from the gradient menu. Press USE to
start making gradients, which takes roughly 10 minutes. &lt;em&gt;From this point onwards,
keep the tubes upright and make no sudden movements with them, so as not to
disturb the gradient.&lt;/em&gt; Remove capillary cap from tube and, using long-nosed
pliers if necessary, place in rotor bucket in bucket rack.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Balance the tubes: balance tube 1 with tube 4, 2 with 5, and 3 with 6.
Placing bucket-tube assembly on scale, remove sucrose gradient from top of tube
as necessary to ensure paired tubes are within 0.1g in mass.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prepared gradients can be stored at 4C for a day or two.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;spin&quot;&gt;Spin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Load sample and assemble rotor: take sample, SW28.1 (or SW28) rotor, 
bucket rack, and 200 ul pipette to ultracentrifuge. Load sample in
each tube by placing filled pipette tip in meniscus at side of tube,
and pipetting slowly; you should see the sample spreading out across
top of liquid. Gently place lid on tube and screw cap on bucket.
Hang buckets in numbered slots on rotor, checking that both hooks
are attached for every bucket.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Set up centrifuge: turn on centrifuge, break vacuum and open
spin chamber. Select 27500 rpm, 3.5hrs, 4C, with vacuum, on
centrifuge controls. Place rotor assembly on axle, and seal
spin chamber. Start centrifuge and fill out centrifuge logbook.
Check on the centrifuge after 15 minutes to ensure it is
running smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After running for 3.5hrs, the centrifuge takes several minutes
to brake. Once the centrifuge has stopped spinning, release the
vacuum, carefully remove rotor from spin chamber and place buckets
in bucket rack.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;set-up-gradient-station&quot;&gt;Set up gradient station&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Take bucket rack with gradients to gradient station, very gently.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Turn on the gradient station, the UV monitor, the fraction collector, 
and the linked computer. Connect the USB cable, start the gradient profiler
program on the computer and enter appropriate parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Flush the line and calibrate the UV monitor: press DRAIN on fraction
collector. On the gradient station, from the initial screen press FRAC, then
FRAC. Hold RINSE on gradient station to flush the line. Half-fill a centrifuge
tube with 10% sucrose buffer, turn front dial so that vacuum plunger descends at
about 0.5 mm/s. Once plunger is a few cm into liquid and drips are coming out of
the fraction collector, press AUTO ZERO on the UV monitor.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;collect-fractions&quot;&gt;Collect fractions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each ultracentrifuge tube with sample:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Initialize fraction collector: ensure there are 30x clean 1.5ml
tubes in the two middle rows of the tube holder. Pre-label the tubes
if desired. Press END, then START, and make sure drip outlet is
above tube 0.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Remove bucket cap, remove centrifuge from bucket using long-nosed
pliers, and attach locking top to centrifuge tube. Place tube in
tube holder on gradient station, locking the tube in place by
rotating the cap to lock in place. Slide tube holder onto mount on
top of gradient station with window facing to the right, and turn
clockwise so window is facing towards you.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On gradient station, press FRAC once or twice to get to the fractionation
menu, then SNGL for single run, and set the parameters to speed = 0.3, distance
= 3.2 (for SW28.1; 2.6 for SW28), and 31 fractions. Rotate front dial to full
counterclockwise position. Move plunger downwards by turning dial to the right
until speed = 1.0 mm/s; move plunger slowly (0.2 mm/s) as it approaches the
gradient surface, so that you can stop (by turning dial fully left) as soon as
the plunger has sealed on the gradient. Press RESET on gradient station. In
subsequent tubes from same run, reset to same position – i.e. 0.0 mm on display 
– from previous tube.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the gradient profiler program on the computer, press RECORD. Then
press START on gradient station.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When finished, remove tubes from fraction collector and label them.
Press EXIT 3 times on gradient station to return to fraction menu,
and remove centrifuge tube from holder. &lt;em&gt;Crucially, save the output
on the computer, and press NEW RUN to record the next gradient.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note that the first 1-3 tubes in the fraction collector are usually
empty, so that the tube number on the rack is offset from
that reported in the gradient profiler software (BioComp 
instructions suggest this is solvable: good luck!). Tube 0 according 
to gradient profiler software is the first filled tube on the fraction 
collector. It may be easiest to label the tubes accordingly, after the 
fractions are collected.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cleanup&quot;&gt;Cleanup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Check &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; equipment for potential sucrose gradient spills and
clean thoroughly with damp cloth and dilute ethanol; this is a very 
sticky spill. In particular, clean the plunger and flush the tubing 
with water.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Flush tubing with a full tube of 50% Ethanol to disinfect (DRAIN on 
fraction collector, from FRAC screen on gradient station lower plunger 
at about 0.5 mm/s).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Store rotor and buckets in cold room, on rotor holding platform.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Anti-RNA blotting with chemiluminescent detection</title>
   <link href="/protocols/protocol/rna-blot"/>
   <updated>2015-10-30T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>/protocols/protocol/rna-blot</id>
   <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;This protocol is for northern blotting/dot-blotting to detect specific
RNAs via chemiluminescence, using biotinylated DNA oligo probes. Gels etc
are optimized for detection of 0.5-4kb mRNA transcripts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of it is adapted from ULTRAhyb-Oligo and Brightstar BioDetect
commercial protocols, or from &lt;em&gt;Nonisotopic Probing, Blotting, and
Sequencing&lt;/em&gt; (Kricka, ed; chapter 5).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For abundant RNAs, it is possible to reduce the lengths of the (many) 
hybridization, wash and block steps while still obtaining a clean blot 
with low background - test probes and sample the slow way first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1X TBE, 0.5X TBE. Make from 10X stock.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;RNase-free agarose&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gel casting, running and electroblotting equipment (BioRad Minigel system,
Biorad Criterion or Protean blotter)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;RNA ladders: ThermoFisher RiboRuler HR (#SM1821) is good for 200-6000nt mRNAs.
DynaMarker® Prestain Marker for RNA High (Biodynamics #DM260) is a prestained
ladder made of polysaccharides useful for seeing the gel run and or successful 
membrane transfer, but it runs larger than advertised length on TBE-agarose gels.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Positively charged nylon membrane (BrightStar-Plus Positively
Charged Nylon Membrane, or Roche 11-209-299-001, or Bio-Rad Zeta-Probe #1620154)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;UV crosslinking box, e.g. Stratalinker.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ULTRAhyb-Oligo buffer (Life/ThermoFisher AM8663)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;DNA oligo probes: 5’ biotinylated, 36-45nt long, 60-75C hybridization
temperature, 45-65% GC-content, in
10uM working solution. Or use biotinylated oligo-dT
probes (Promega #Z5261) at 5 pmol/uL for mRNA.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stringency wash buffer: 2X SSC (300mM NaCl, 30mM sodium citrate, pH
7.0), 0.5% SDS. Make from 20X SSC stock (Life/ThermoFisher, AM9770).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NB strip buffer: 0.1X SSC, 0.5% SDS.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Streptavidin-AP conjugate (Life/Thermo Fisher #S921)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CDP-Star® Luminescent Substrate (0.25 mM Ready-To-Use), (Life/ThermoFisher #T2146)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wash buffer: 1X PBS, 0.5% SDS. Make a 5X concentrate with 5X PBS and 2.5% SDS.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Blocking buffer: 1X PBS, 0.5% SDS, 0.1% I-Block reagent.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Assay buffer: 0.1M DEA (diethanolamine), 1mM MgCl2, pH 10.0.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: the BrightStar BioDetect Nonisotopic Detection Kit (Life/ThermoFisher AM1930), 
contained CDP-star, Strep-AP, 5X wash buffer, 1X blocking buffer, and 10X assay buffer, but was not 
produced after 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make wash, block and assay buffer fresh every month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;be-fastidious-about-cleanliness-and-avoiding-degradation&quot;&gt;Be fastidious about cleanliness and avoiding degradation!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Use RNAse-free equipment and solutions to run gel and transfer so
you get a clear single band, and do not degrade your sample.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Only ever touch the membrane with forceps, i.e. not with your skin,
sweat, etc, to avoid background.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dot-blot&quot;&gt;Dot Blot&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To check if your probes and buffers are working without running a gel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gently pipette 10uL of each RNA sample onto positively charged nylon membrane
on vacuum (fritted glass plate). Dry membrane.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;northern-blotting&quot;&gt;Northern Blotting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cast a 1.5% agarose gel in 1X TBE buffer with 1:10000 SYBR safe and
allow to set.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Put 1uL (or other measured amount) of each RNA sample into total
10uL of 1X RNA loading buffer (NEB). Heat the tubes at 65 C for 5 min
to denature RNA and then immediately place the tubes on ice.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Load samples on the gel along with 5uL RNA ladder/markers. Run the gel 
in 1X TBE buffer at 100 V for 30min, or until the first bromophenol 
blue dye reaches the bottom of the gel. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Turn off the current, remove the gel, and transfer the RNA onto a
positively-charged nylon membrane. Use a pencil to mark the &lt;em&gt;sample&lt;/em&gt;
side of the membrane. Assemble gel sandwich according to picture on blotter instructions
(RNA is negatively charged, so gel near negative electrode and
membrane near positive electrode), use a standard Western blotting
apparatus with 0.5X TBE buffer at 1 amp for 1 h. Trim off the
portions of the gel that do not contain the samples to decrease the
size of the membrane and use of smaller amounts of reagents in
subsequent steps.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Crosslink RNA to the membrane by UV at 300 mJ/cm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;; keep the
membrane wet during crosslinking. Then dry the membrane; sample side
faces &lt;em&gt;up&lt;/em&gt; throughout.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hybridization&quot;&gt;Hybridization&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If necessary, reheat ULTRAhyb-Oligo to 42-68 C to dissolve all
precipitated material.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prehybridize the blot for 10 min at 42 C with gentle agitation (incubator 
at 42 C with 40rpm shaking). Use 1 mL ULTRAhyb-Oligo Hybridization
Buffer per 10 cm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; of membrane; volumes shown here are for
minigel-sized blot, about 100 cm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;. Be certain that enough solution 
is present to keep the membrane uniformly wet for all subsequent steps.
[step:prehyb]&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add 5 nM of the end labeled oligonucleotide (0.5 ul of
10 uM working solution per mL of buffer). Since it is
important that undiluted probe solution does not touch the membrane,
pour the ULTRAhyb-Oligo solution from the prehybridization into a 50
mL conical tube, add the labeled probe, mix by swirling, and then
immediately pour the solution back into the container with the blot.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hybridize overnight (6-24hr) at 42 C with gentle agitation. It may be
possible to reduce the hybridization time down to 1hr for detection of
relatively abundant RNA.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wash the blot 2x30 min. Pipette off hybridization solution 
&lt;em&gt;and save in 10mL tube&lt;/em&gt;, this can be reused multiple (~5) times. 
Immediately pour at least 50 mL stringency wash buffer onto the blot 
and incubate at 42 C for 30 min with gentle agitation. Repeat with fresh 
stringency wash buffer.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;detection&quot;&gt;Detection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Measure the surface area of your membrane to determine the amounts
of the washing and assay buffers needed. For example, for a 10 x 10 cm membrane (100
cm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;), 100 mL of washing buffer and 30 mL of assay buffer are
needed (the volumes below are given for a 100 cm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; membrane).
Place the membrane sample side up in a plastic box of similar size, 
at room temperature  on a rocking shaker at medium speed (10-20 rockings/min).
Do not allow the membrane to dry throughout the entire procedure.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wash the membrane 2 times, 5 min each, in 20 mL 1X washing buffer.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wash the membrane 2 times, 5 min each, in 10 mL 1X blocking buffer.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wash the membrane once for 30 min in 20 mL 1X blocking buffer.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Incubate the membrane for 30 min in 10 mL of conjugate solution
(10 mL blocking buffer plus 1 ul of streptavidin-alkaline phosphatase 
conjugate).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wash the membrane once for 15 min in 20 mL 1X blocking buffer.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wash the membrane 3 times, 15 min each, in 20 mL 1X washing buffer.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wash the membrane 2 times, 2 min each, in 15 mL 1X assay buffer.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Incubate the membrane in enough CDP-star solution to cover, about
1mL, for 5 min. Rotate by hand to make sure that the solution evenly
covers the entire membrane.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Take out the membrane with forceps. Let the excess of CDP-star
solution drip off, place the membrane on clear plastic wrap and
wrap, ensuring no air bubbles are left.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Image the membrane on the Chemi-doc or other digital imager. Use
chemiluminescent detection with signal accumulation mode, for
example 45 images, 900 s. The CDP-star reaches peak light emission in
2-4 h, and the light emission persists at the high level for several
days, so you may get a better image by waiting an hour
to image. SYBR safe also tends to transfer to the membrane with
rRNA, sometimes enough to be seen by the naked eye, but is
visualizable on Cy3 channel; unfortunately Xylene Cyanol
is also transferred, visible as a lower-molecular
weight bright blur on this channel so tRNA is not visible.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stripping-and-re-probing&quot;&gt;Stripping and re-probing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Membranes may be stripped and re-probed multiple times (at least 4);
they can be left in wash or block solution overnight, or frozen in
plastic wrap at -20 C for weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Remove membrane from plastic wrap, place membrane in a plastic tray
that can survive 100 C liquids, covered by a minimal amount of NB
strip buffer. Do not dry membrane, which may stick previous probes
to membrane.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Twice: Heat 50mL NB strip buffer to boiling, in the microwave. Empty
previous liquid, and pour boiling strip buffer over membrane
in tray. Allow to cool to room temperature on rocker, about
15 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Restart hybridization with new probes and continue as before.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For smaller RNA (50-500b) use a Bio-Rad Criterion TBE-Urea 5%
acrylamide gel with 1X TBE buffer, be sure to wash wells with TBE 
before loading. Run at 200 V for 60min. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Supernatant/pellet fractionation of budding yeast cells by cryogenic lysis</title>
   <link href="/protocols/protocol/yeast-lysis"/>
   <updated>2015-07-23T00:00:00+12:00</updated>
   <id>/protocols/protocol/yeast-lysis</id>
   <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;For studies of protein aggregation, few techniques are simpler than two-phase fractionation by centrifugation: big stuff (aggregates) pellets, small stuff (unaggregated proteins) stays in the supernatant. Breaking open cells (lysis) can alter or even cause protein aggregation. For yeast cells, which have a tough cell wall, lysis requires a lot of force. We and others find that cryogenic milling does a good job in lysing most cells without causing aggregation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With minor adaptations, we have applied the same lysis/fractionation to E. coli, cyanobacteria, mammalian cell culture, squid axoplasm, and alternative yeasts. Appearance of membrane proteins in the pellet and cytoplasmic proteins the sup is a good quality control for unstressed samples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on Mike Dion and Allan Drummond’s 2011 protocols, with extensive modiﬁcations by Edward Wallace with help from Quincey Justman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;protocol&quot;&gt;Protocol&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;prepare&quot;&gt;Prepare&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;soluble protein buﬀer (SPB; 20mM HEPES-KOH pH7.4, 120mM KCl, 2mM
EDTA, 0.2mM DTT, 1:100 PMSF, 1:100 protease inhibitors cocktail IV).
Make stock of salt and buﬀer, add DTT and inhibitors shortly before
use, and chill.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;total protein buﬀer (TPB; 20mM HEPES-NaOH pH7.4, 150mM NaCl, 5mM
EDTA, 3% SDS, 1:100 PMSF, 2mM DTT, 1:1000 protease inhibitors IV).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;insoluble protein buﬀer (IPB; 8M Urea, 20mM HEPES-NaOH pH7.4, 150mM
NaCl, 2% SDS, 2mM EDTA, 2mM DTT, 1:100 PMSF, 1:1000 protease
inhibitors IV.). Mix fresh daily the urea, DTT, and inhibitors (use a stock solution of other ingredients) and keep at room temperature.
Use 250 μL IPB per sample, and note that Urea is slow to
dissolve, and foaming will make ~25% of the solution unusable.
IPB solidiﬁes at 4°C due to urea and SDS; also, don’t
substitute KCl as it precipitates SDS even at RT.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;thead&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2 mL (~4 samples)&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;13 mL (~20 samples)&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;/thead&gt;
      &lt;tbody&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;950 μL&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6.2  mL&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;H2O&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;200 μL&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1.3  mL&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;20% SDS (w/v)&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;40 μL&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;260 μL&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1M HEPES-NaOH pH7.4&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8 μL&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;52 μL&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;0.5M EDTA&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;75 μL&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;390 μL&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5M NaCl&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;20 μL&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;130 μL&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;100mM PMSF&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4 μL&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;26 μL&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1M DTT&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2 μL&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;13 μL&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;protease inhibitors IV&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;0.96g&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6.24g&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;urea&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;/tbody&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For heat treatment, pre-warm water bath to 46°C or pre-warm
media as required.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Appropriate numbers of safe-lok tubes loaded with 7mm steel balls,
racked in liquid nitrogen (LN2).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pre-chill a centrifuge, also label and lay out all tubes and
equipment in advance as the protocol moves very quickly
once started.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Protocol can be paused and samples stored at -80°C when cells
have been ﬂash-frozen (step &lt;a href=&quot;#step-flashfreeze&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;), and after cells have
been ground in mixer mill (step &lt;a href=&quot;#step-powder&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h3 id=&quot;sample-growth&quot;&gt;Sample Growth&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For each strain, inoculate a 3  mL pre-culture of SC-complete medium
with a single yeast colony and incubate overnight at 30with shaking
or rotation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Inoculate overnight culture to OD&lt;sub&gt;600&lt;/sub&gt; ~ 0.01 in
SC-complete medium in a baffled flask, grow to 4×10&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;
cells/ mL (OD&lt;sub&gt;600&lt;/sub&gt; ~ 0.45) at 30°C with 200rpm shaking.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h3 id=&quot;sample-harvesting-and-lysis&quot;&gt;Sample Harvesting and Lysis&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Transfer 2×10&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt; cells to a 50 mL conical tube (50  mL of a
4×10&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt; cells/ mL culture).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spin at 2500 g for 30s in a swinging bucket rotor at RT. The end of
this spin marks the start of the timed treatment duration. Gently
decant and discard supernatant. For heat shock treatment, hold tube
containing pellet in waterbath at desired temperature for desired
time; alternatively, transfer to pre-warmed media for desired time
and end by spinning as described.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Resuspend pellet in 1 mL ice-cold SPB, on ice, and transfer to pre-chilled
1.5 mL tube.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spin at 5,000 g, 4°C, for 30 seconds.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Resuspend new pellet in 150 μL lysis buffer.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;step-flashfreeze&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 
Drip 100 μL of resuspended pellet onto upper
wall of tube containing steel ball, still racked in LN2. Goal is to
get a nugget of frozen material on the wall, and to avoid dripping
the material around the ball and thus freezing the ball to the
bottom of the tube; having some LN2 remaining in the tube helps.
Place the remaining 100 μL of resuspended pellet in a tube for total
protein extraction: process, or freeze, immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Place tubes at -80°C; when all LN2 has boiled out of tube (listen – if
any popping or hissing, keep waiting), snap tube closed caref μLly,
away from other tubes. Keep at -80°C or lower. (Any remaining LN2 in tube will cause tube to explode open and fire the stainless steel ball into
your iPad, brain, colleague, or other important equipment.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rack the tube into the PTFE 2 mL tube adaptor for the Retsch Mixer
Mill MM400 (Retsch #22.008.0005) and submerge the entire assembly
in LN2. Agitate for 4x90 seconds at 30 Hz in a Retsch Mixer
Mill MM400, returning sample holder to LN2 between sessions.
Complete lysis produces fine snowy powder in the tube.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;step-powder&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 
Remove sample tubes from LN2, tap on bench to
release powder from lid, and pop the caps to relieve pressure.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add 400 μL SPB to each tube, thaw on ice with
occasional vortexing, and as soon as possible extract ball with
a magnet. (We rinse balls in methanol and store in 50% ethanol.)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h3 id=&quot;supernatant-fraction-extraction&quot;&gt;Supernatant fraction extraction&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spin at 3000 g for 30 seconds (clarification step) to remove whole
cells and very large aggregates.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Decant clarified liquid into a 1.5 mL microcentrifuge tube. If
troubleshooting, keep the 3,000g pellet and process it alongside the
insoluble fraction; this end product is the &lt;em&gt;unclarified fraction&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spin at 100,000 g for 20 minutes (fixed-angle TLA-55 rotor at 40,309
rpm, 4, in a Beckman Coulter Optimax tabletop  ultracentrifuge).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Decant supernatant into a 1.5 mL microcentrifuge tube: this is the
&lt;em&gt;Supernatant fraction&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Take 10 μL aliquot of soluble fraction and mix with 2X Laemmli
buffer; use this to run a protein gel and assess protein integrity.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h3 id=&quot;pellet-fraction-extraction&quot;&gt;Pellet fraction extraction&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Violently snap pellet to clear remaining liquid.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add 500 μL soluble protein buffer (SPB) and vortex.
(The pellet may not resuspend; that’s fine.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spin at 100,000 g for 20 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Discard supernatant, clear residual liquid with a hard snap.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add 250 μL insoluble protein buffer (IPB); note this
means insoluble sample is relatively 2X concentrated to others.
Process samples in IPB at room temperature to maintain solubility of
the Urea.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dislodge the pellet with a pipet tip, Vortex until pellet dissolves,
10-15 minutes for clarified samples.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spin at 20,000 g, RT, for 5 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Decant supernatant into a 1.5 mL microcentrifuge tube: this is the
&lt;em&gt;Pellet fraction&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h3 id=&quot;total-protein-extraction&quot;&gt;Total protein extraction&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add 400 μL TPB to each total protein tube. Incubate
at 95°C with 500rpm mixing for 20 min.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Vortex vigorously for 15 min.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spin at 6000 g, RT, 1 min. Take supernatant; this is the &lt;em&gt;Total
protein fraction&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h3 id=&quot;measure-protein&quot;&gt;Measure protein&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Run a 4-15% SDS-page gel; load roughly 5-10 μL of
total and soluble fractions. Make aliquots for further analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more information, western blot against known stress-aggregating proteins (e.g. Pab1).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chloroform-methanol extract protein from each fraction for mass spectrometry analysis. We use reductive dimethylation following tryptic digestion for post-sample-collection isotopic labeling.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Disaggregation assay data visualization</title>
   <link href="/data/postheat-disaggregation-yeast-visualization"/>
   <updated>2015-07-23T00:00:00+12:00</updated>
   <id>/data/postheat-disaggregation-yeast-visualization</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Interactive data visualization for disaggregation and new-synthesis data from &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/paper/endogenous-aggregates&quot;&gt;our 2015 paper on heat-triggered protein aggregation in yeast&lt;/a&gt;, Figure 6. (Aggregation data visualization is &lt;a href=&quot;/data/heat-aggregation-yeast-visualization&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choose detected proteins by official yeast name, from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.yeastgenome.org/&quot;&gt;SGD&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cells were grown at 30°C, shifted to labeled media, heat-shocked for 10 minutes at 42°C, moved back to 30°C for recovery, and protein in 100,000g supernatant measured. Y-axis is ratio of protein in supernatant between treated and control cells, X-axis is either time or temperature of shock. Linetype reflects isotopic label on the amino acids: solid line is arginine/lysine imported before onset of heat shock, dashed line is imported after shock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;900&quot; height=&quot;720&quot; src=&quot;https://dadrummond.shinyapps.io/ratiosup_shiny/&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Aggregation assay data visualization</title>
   <link href="/data/heat-aggregation-yeast-visualization"/>
   <updated>2015-07-23T00:00:00+12:00</updated>
   <id>/data/heat-aggregation-yeast-visualization</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Interactive data visualization for data from &lt;a href=&quot;/papers/paper/endogenous-aggregates&quot;&gt;our 2015 paper on heat-triggered protein aggregation in yeast&lt;/a&gt;, Figure 1. (Disaggregation data visualization is &lt;a href=&quot;/data/postheat-disaggregation-yeast-visualization&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choose detected proteins by official yeast name, from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.yeastgenome.org/&quot;&gt;SGD&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Y-axis is proportion of protein in 100,000g supernatant, X-axis is either time or temperature of shock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;900&quot; height=&quot;720&quot; src=&quot;https://dadrummond.shinyapps.io/psup_shiny/&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Chloroform-methanol extraction of proteins</title>
   <link href="/protocols/protocol/chloroform-methanol-precipitation"/>
   <updated>2015-04-21T00:00:00+12:00</updated>
   <id>/protocols/protocol/chloroform-methanol-precipitation</id>
   <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Detergents, like SDS, and salts, like NaCl, can disrupt liquid chromatography/tandem mass spectrometry (LC-MS/MS) studies by interfering with chemistry and clogging columns and spray needles. Precipitation with chloroform and methanol results in dry protein material, free of salt and detergent, which perform sweetly during these critical steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;protocol&quot;&gt;Protocol&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To 100 µL protein sample (~100µg protein) in a 1.5mL eppendorf tube:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add 400 µL methanol and vortex thoroughly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add 100 µL chloroform and vortex.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add 300 µL H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O—mixture will become cloudy with precipitate—and vortex.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Centrifuge 1 minute @ 14,000g. Result is three layers: a large aqueous layer on top, a circular flake of protein in the interphase, and a smaller chloroform layer at the bottom.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remove top aqueous layer carefully, trying not to disturb the protein flake.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add 400 µL methanol and vortex.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Centrifuge 5 minutes @ 20,000g, which will slam dandruffy precipitate against the tube wall.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remove as much methanol as possible. Be careful, because the pellet is delicate. You should be able to remove all but a few µL of methanol with care, which will speed drying.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dry under vacuum.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adapted from Wessel, D. and Flügge, U.I. (1984) &lt;em&gt;Anal. Biochem.&lt;/em&gt; 138 141–143.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Evolution of protein synthesis</title>
   <link href="/projects/project/selection-on-translation"/>
   <updated>2015-04-04T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>/projects/project/selection-on-translation</id>
   <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Natural selection on protein synthesis sculpts genomes in profound ways.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Protein misfolding and gene expression</title>
   <link href="/projects/project/misfolding-and-expression"/>
   <updated>2015-04-03T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>/projects/project/misfolding-and-expression</id>
   <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Protein misfolding generates toxic molecules and stimulates cellular stress responses.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Engineering self-assembling proteins</title>
   <link href="/projects/project/assembly-engineering"/>
   <updated>2015-04-03T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>/projects/project/assembly-engineering</id>
   <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Discovering self-assembling proteins in cells allows us to exploit triggerable assembly for useful tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Regulation by massive molecular assembly</title>
   <link href="/projects/project/stress-agg"/>
   <updated>2015-04-02T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
   <id>/projects/project/stress-agg</id>
   <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Stress triggers proteins to clump together into massive assemblies.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>
